<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sustainability on </title>
    <link>https://darrylcauldwell.github.io/categories/sustainability/</link>
    <description>Recent content in sustainability on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://darrylcauldwell.github.io/categories/sustainability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sustainable Shopping</title>
      <link>https://darrylcauldwell.github.io/post/sustainable-shopping/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://darrylcauldwell.github.io/post/sustainable-shopping/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;Our shopping affects people, animals and the environment. Every purchase we make has huge repercussions down the supply chain socially, economically and environmentally. Over recent years we have all become much more aware of our impact to the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;shop-locally&#34;&gt;Shop Locally&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was raised in rural UK where my parents where shopkeepers. During this time I came to realize the power of community at the heart of which is typically small, independent businesses. When shopping locally you regularly share a communal space with other people in the community this naturally leads to communication and forming of relationships. Small, independent businesses are sources of employment and providers and consumers of goods and services that sustain the local economy. When you shop at chain retailers, most of the money will go back to the business elsewhere, whereas the money you spend at local businesses will directly go back into the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wife and I are lucky enough to live in a small market town which has a good collection of small, local businesses. Most people who are grew up in the town are cogizant to the importance of small, independent businesses and support them with their custom. However as more people move to the rural town from cities their culture of supermarkets and then low-cost supermarkets has spread outwards too. This has led to the collapse of many small, local businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To retain our unique communities and maintain a healthy local economy we should all look to shop and support small, local businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;shop-sustainably&#34;&gt;Shop Sustainably&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shopping sustainably means shopping at ethical brands and retailers - and not just those that brand themselves as &amp;rsquo;ethical&amp;rsquo; without actually being too kind to the environment. Standad shopping practices, especially the clothing industry is largely opaque, exploitative and environmentally damaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When buying clothes, it is important to always read the fine print to see what materials your clothing is actually made of. Synthetic materials like polyester, nylon, and acrylic take hundreds of years to decompose. Those materials account for a large chunk of the clothing that’s currently sitting in landfills. Plus, synthetics require plastic and chemicals to make, and these directly contaminate water supplies. Choosing all-natural fabrics is one way to work toward a more sustainable wardrobe but also a more economical wardrobe as these pieces will last far longer. Look for organic cotton, hemp, Tencel, ethically-raised wool, and other natural fibres!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there are some options for sustainable shopping local to where I live there are much more options available for home delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When its not possible to shop locally rather than travel to a city I generally turn to the internet. While investigating sustainable living I&amp;rsquo;ve collected a series of bookmarks as I&amp;rsquo;ve shopped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fairtrader.info/&#34;&gt;Fair trader&lt;/a&gt; is a volunteer-run co-operative shop in Holmfirth, West Yorkshire. They stock an exciting range of fashion accessories, jewellery, food and drink, clothing, homewares, toiletries, greetings cards and toys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.miterro.com/&#34;&gt;Mi Terro&lt;/a&gt; re-engineers food waste into sustainable materials for example waste milk into t-shirts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ethicalsuperstore.com/&#34;&gt;Ethical Superstore&lt;/a&gt; offers products across multiple product categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bambooclothing.co.uk&#34;&gt;Bamboo Clothing&lt;/a&gt; offers clothing made from bamboo really good for yoga and gym wear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lefrik.com&#34;&gt;Lefrik&lt;/a&gt; offers bags and backpacks made from recycled plastic bottles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.weavergreen.com/&#34;&gt;Weaver Green&lt;/a&gt; offers rugs and textiles made from recycled plastic bottles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.veloculture.co.uk&#34;&gt;Velo Culture&lt;/a&gt; offers belts and wallets made from recycled bicycle innertubes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cycleofgood.com&#34;&gt;Cycle For Good&lt;/a&gt; operates the Elephant Bike initative where if you buy a recycled bike from them they give one to someone in Malawi via their social enterprise scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.yogabloke.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Yoga Bloke&lt;/a&gt; offers various sustainable yoga equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://global.prana.com&#34;&gt;PrAna&lt;/a&gt; offers sustainable yoga clothing, US but ships to UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.napapijri.co.uk&#34;&gt;Napapijri&lt;/a&gt; offers sustainable clothing including some really nice coats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rapanuiclothing.com&#34;&gt;Rapanui&lt;/a&gt; offers sustainable clothing range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seatowel.eu&#34;&gt;SeaTowel&lt;/a&gt; offers towels made from platic collected by fishermen from the sea during fishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mamoq.com&#34;&gt;momoq&lt;/a&gt; offers sustainable clothing range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://finisterre.com&#34;&gt;finisterre&lt;/a&gt; offers sustainable clothing range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.komodo.co.uk&#34;&gt;komodo&lt;/a&gt; offers sustainable clothing range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nomadsclothing.com&#34;&gt;nomads&lt;/a&gt; offers sustainable clothing range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wearethought.com&#34;&gt;thought&lt;/a&gt; offers sustainable clothing range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://williamlennon.co.uk/&#34;&gt;William Lennon&lt;/a&gt; englands last working boot maker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://veganoutfitters.com/&#34;&gt;Vegan Outfitters&lt;/a&gt; general clothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.livecoco.com/&#34;&gt;LiveCoco&lt;/a&gt; eco dental care products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bbcearth.teemill.com/circular-collection/&#34;&gt;BBC Earth&lt;/a&gt; recycled tshirts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twisted-creations.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Twisted Willow Creations&lt;/a&gt; garden willow sculptures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are not endorsements, just a collection of online stores I have either bought or considered buying something from.  If you have any recomendations of good places to shop online for delivery to UK do let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vegetarianuary 2020</title>
      <link>https://darrylcauldwell.github.io/post/vegetarianuary/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://darrylcauldwell.github.io/post/vegetarianuary/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;I have under taken my personal challenges over the years and the occasion of a new decade seemed a good reason to undertake another. I was inspired to look at doing this by my daughter who is an avid fan of science and is very data-driven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year in the middle of summer at the Bluedot science and music festival we found out about the impact of dairy om the planet and took the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oatly.com/uk/ditch-milk&#34;&gt;Oatly ditch-milk&lt;/a&gt; pledge and both went dairy-free for 72 hours. A day or so later while playing in the park with all of her friends they all had ice-cream but she stood by her pledge and refused, I was very proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experienc of going dairy-free led to us as a family spoking around the subject alot and researched some facts and figures. Ultimatley we as a family didn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;lsquo;ditch dairy&amp;rsquo;. It did influence us and we moved to regularly use almond milk for cereals albeit maintaining a smaller supply of cows milk for hot drinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal is to move to a plant-based diet for January to encourages further discussion within our family about what we eat and the pro&amp;rsquo;s and con&amp;rsquo;s of a plant-based diet. We will hopefully all learn something from this and will maintain some aspects for the longer term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Types of plant-based diets include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lacto-ovo vegetarians ( plant based but includes dairy foods and eggs )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ovo vegetarians ( plant based but includes eggs )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vegans ( plant based only )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My original thought was to take part in &lt;a href=&#34;https://uk.veganuary.com/&#34;&gt;veganuary&lt;/a&gt;. After reading around the full extent of what going vegan means and looking at our current &amp;rsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; lifestyle. With any form of goal-setting the goals have to be specific, measurable, achievable, relavent and time bound. I am not sure it is achievable to change so much overnight to become vegan, but maybe this experience will better equip for a future endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measurable Goal&lt;/strong&gt; - Lacto-ovo vegetarian between 1st and 31st January&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://darrylcauldwell.github.io/images/veg-family.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Family Vegtarian Meal&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;12000-steps-daily-average&#34;&gt;12,000 Steps Daily Average&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I an lucky enough to live in a natually beautiful location. It is easy during the winter months when it is dark both before and after work to reduce what we do. Jogging and running when it is slippery can easily lead to minor injury. By leaving the car and walking I think it should be possible for me to average walking 6 miles / &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.verywellfit.com/how-many-walking-steps-are-in-a-mile-3435916&#34;&gt;12,000 steps&lt;/a&gt; per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measurable Goal&lt;/strong&gt; - Average 12,000 steps per day between 1st and 31st January&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://darrylcauldwell.github.io/images/veg-12k.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jogging&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;detoxification&#34;&gt;Detoxification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tried some very focussed detox programs over the years. I do not intend to follow a particular defined program during January. I do intend to take opportunity to do something in this area. Detoxification is about resting, cleansing and nourishing the body from the inside out. Processing alcohol and cafine puts a strain on the organs. It is easy to increase drinking alcohol and cafine over time and useful every now and then to abstain. Whichever detox program I have followed they all have all included &amp;rsquo;lemon water&amp;rsquo; for helping your digestion, flushes out toxins and cleanses the liver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measurable Goal&lt;/strong&gt; - Zero alcohol per day between 1st and 31st January&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measurable Goal&lt;/strong&gt; - No more than one cup of coffee per day between 1st and 31st January&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measurable Goal&lt;/strong&gt; - Glass of lemon water per day between 1st and 31st January&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://darrylcauldwell.github.io/images/veg-detox.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Detox&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;yoga&#34;&gt;Yoga&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried yoga first while working in India some fifteen years ago. Being on the tall side I&amp;rsquo;ve always been conscious of my back health and found yoga helped. I used to regularly attend yoga sessions in evenings. I changed jobs and for a while was a remote member of a team based on the US West Coast and team meetings clashed.  More recently our team has restructured and I am now part of a team based in EMEA. Since the re-organization I had not got around to re-joining the yoga sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measurable Goal&lt;/strong&gt; - Attend at least three of the four weekly yoga sessions between 1st and 31st January&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://darrylcauldwell.github.io/images/veg-yoga.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Yoga&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fitism&#34;&gt;FITISM&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a member of local gym called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fitism.co.uk/&#34;&gt;FITISM&lt;/a&gt; I have a balanced membership focussing on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fitism.co.uk/classes&#34;&gt;classes&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fitism.co.uk/blog/nutrition&#34;&gt;nutrition&lt;/a&gt;. I focussed on high intensity circuit type training classes. Three weeks ago I slipped on some ince and fell down some steps cracking a rib and a tooth. Soft tissue damage to the chest meant it was painful to do any classes. As the soft tissue has repaired I have been able to progress from walking to light jogging. I am now mostly comfortable but the cracked rib still makes me aware of its displeasure if I laugh, sneeze, cough or over extend a twist. One of the class types offered is RIDE which looks to be essentially spinning, I am hopeful this class type should be achievable in January. I am lucky to train in such a fun, energetic, competitive, yet encouraging environment, I feel confident together we will find a suitable class I can regularly attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measurable Goal&lt;/strong&gt; - Attend at least two FITISM classes per week between 1st and 31st January&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://darrylcauldwell.github.io/images/veg-fitism.png&#34; alt=&#34;FITISM&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
